

Education

BSc Computer Science - Upper 2nd Class with Honours in Computer Science, University of Essex, GB

Languages

English - Fluent

Oliver Mitchell

United Kingdom

Profile

Oliver is a full stack developer, providing technical leadership and promoting industry best practices, currently working in a DevSecOps scrum team, building full-stack web applications through continuous integration and continuous delivery.

Oliver has previously worked on deliveries of Oracle APEX, React web applications, Java RESTful APIs and a data exploitation platform built with Java micro-services and IBM Watson analytics.

Key skills

Java & Spring Boot
JavaScript, ECMAScript & React
Jest, JUnit, Cypress & Cucumber.js
Cloud (Amazon Web Services)
Containerisation (Docker, Kubernetes, OpenShift)
CI/CD (Terraform, Ansible, Jenkins, SonarQube, Nexus & Git)
Oracle PL/SQL & SQL
Oracle APEX
Unix & Linux shell scripting
Python
Blue Prism accredited robotic process automation developer
Microsoft Power Platform (Power Apps & Power Automate)
IBM Watson Explorer Content Analytics
Agile scrum & kanban

Key courses and training

Certified SAFe® 4 Agilist Mental Health First Aider

Mental Health First Aid Adult course (2020)
SAFe® 4.6 Agilist Exam (2019)
Leading SAFe® (2019)
Enterprise Design Thinking Foundations (2018)
Automation Fundamentals (2018)
Career Coaches Academy (2018)
IBM Global Blue Consulting (2016)
Agile Scrum Master Introduction (2015)
Blue Prism Accredited Developer Examination (2015)
Blue Prism Foundation Training Course (2015)
ITIL Version 3 Foundation Examination (2008)

Work experience



Managing Developer

IBM Client Innovation Centre - UK, United Kingdom | Jul 2018 - Present

Oliver is working as a technical lead and full stack developer, using JavaScript, Java and relational databases in conjunction with DevSecOps and continuous integration tools to create applications on cloud services and deliver to client infrastructure.

Line Manager

IBM Client Innovation Centre - UK, United Kingdom | Jul 2017 - Jan 2020

Oliver was responsible for eight CIC employees, ensuring their probation periods, promotion cases and day to day administration tasks are processed efficiently.

Senior Developer

IBM Client Innovation Centre - UK, United Kingdom | Nov 2016 - Jun 2018

Oliver was working as a full stack developer, using JavaScript, Java and relational databases in conjunction with DevSecOps and continuous integration tools to create applications on cloud services and deliver to client infrastructure.

Automation Developer

Aviva, United Kingdom | Feb 2015 - May 2016

In 2015 Oliver learned to build software robots, using the Blue Prism platform, with the goal of automating repetitive business processes. This proved to be very rewarding; not only did he learn to use new tools but he gained a better understanding of applications and how they could be improved.

This was a role he performed parallel to being the Oracle Database Team Lead.

In December 2015 he passed the Blue Prism Accredited Developer exam, with distinction.

Notable Work

Built a reusable framework of objects for automating processes through key business applications such as:

- IBM Mainframe
- Siebel
- IBM Content Manager eClient
- Microsoft Exchange
- Microsoft Excel

Oracle Database Team Lead

Aviva, United Kingdom | Jul 2008 - Oct 2016

Oliver's primary role was to develop and support database solutions, using mostly agile methodologies, in a complex, heavily integrated, estate hosted both in traditional data centres and with cloud providers.

Oliver developed and supported complex applications, written in Oracle PL/



SQL, SQL and Oracle Forms, integrated with various other legacy and modern applications including: Siebel, IBM Mainframe, RedHat JBoss, RedHat Fuse and SAS. Integration methods ranged from overnight legacy Oracle and Unix batch suites, using FTP, to web services and direct connections, for real-time interfaces.

From 2013 to 2016 Oliver was the Oracle Database Team Lead and subject matter expert, for the health insurance business unit, responsible for platform management, database solutions design and ensuring development followed industry best practices using both waterfall and Agile methodologies. Oliver was also responsible for offshoring menial support and development to a small team across sites in Bangalore and Pune, for whom Oliver performed technical mentorship and task management, ensuring the offshore team members had the skills and knowledge to fulfil their roles and progress their own careers, to the point where they were mostly self-sufficient.

Notable Work

- Upgraded an Oracle Forms application to use database web services, to communicate with IBM Mainframe, rather than the IBM SNA protocol.
- Worked with a 3rd party to develop enhancements to their application, delivering essential business functionality and allowing integration with existing applications.
- Developed PL/SQL to convert XML objects into tabular data, allowing previously dark data to be exploited by the Business Intelligence team.
- Created PL/SQL "APIs" for middleware to consume data securely and efficiently. This has the added benefits of maintaining data quality and providing a reusable interface to the data.
- Planned the redevelopment a legacy Oracle Forms and Reports 6 application in Oracle APEX 5, enlisting the services of an Oracle Platinum Partner.

Product Support Engineer

Aircom International, United Kingdom | Dec 2007 - Jul 2008

Oliver joined the support team with little knowledge of their software, or their market, and quickly familiarised himself with mobile network technologies and the complex network planning tools Aircom provided to operators the world over.

Daily tasks ranged from troubleshooting various versions of software, to interrogating databases, to working alongside the developers and customers from some of the largest network operators, in the UK and Europe, to identify software defects.

Systems Consultant

Saga, United Kingdom | Jan 2006 - Dec 2007

Oliver joined Saga as a Claims Handler, for their motor insurance call centre, but secured a secondment to IT, to work as a Systems Consultant. As he quickly settled into the role, demonstrating his abilities, he was made permanent after only 6 months.

He worked as a developer on a wide variety of projects, including taking responsibility for the Oracle Forms client upgrade (from 4.5 to 10), in the



migration of the primary insurance system from Oracle Database 7 to 9.

Assignment history

Lead Developer

Public Sector | Jul 2022 - Present

A rainbow team of developers from across the public sector and different suppliers brought together to build secure Oracle APEX applications.

Contribution: Oliver is responsible for designing the Oracle Database schemas, the Oracle APEX user experience and general coding standards. Oliver also works directly with the Oracle APEX technical lead, security architects and client stakeholders to ensure the applications meet business and security requirements.

Technical Lead

Public Sector | Feb 2021 - Jul 2022

A scrum team positioned to deliver a full stack replacement asset management system in a wider HR and ERP (enterprise resource planning) programme for the public sector.

The application will integrate with the new ERP system and all existing security infrastructure.

Contribution: Oliver designed the application stack using open source laaS and PaaS offerings wherever possible, to enable development in public cloud and production deployment to the client's container platform.

All components used automated testing frameworks and a CI/CD pipeline to enable fast and reliable delivery of container images for deployment.

Oliver also mentored 3 of the 4 other developers, who have not worked in a scrum team or in an IBM public sector project before, to ensure they created a usable and maintainable product and followed DevSecOps best practices.

Developer

Public Sector | Jan 2021 - Mar 2021

A temporary assignment to an existing mature Oracle APEX development team.

Oliver was responsible for mentoring a client apprentice developer in delivering a bespoke application to manage the business' incidents and shift handovers.

Contribution: Oliver worked with an apprentice developer, teaching them a wide array of modern software engineering techniques, enabling them to become a cross functional developer and deliver value to the business quickly and predictably. This has included database design, interface and user experience, automated testing, DevSecOps and CI/CD.

Technical Lead

Public Sector | Jun 2020 - Jan 2021

A new capability to deliver automation solutions in the public sector.



Oliver was responsible for robotic process automation (RPA) software life-cycle, as well as supporting junior team members in developing their core skills to become well rounded software engineers.

Contribution: Oliver created a Blue Prism development environment in AWS with infrastructure managed by Terraform, to allow fast and reliable deployments into any account.

Oliver worked with junior developers, improving their DevSecOps skills, CI/CD skills and encouraged software engineering best practices that enabled them to be productive on this and future assignments.

Technical Lead

Private Sector | Oct 2019 - Jun 2020

Project name: Falcon

An experimental endeavour to deliver a full stack cloud application to exploit publicly and commercially available Cyber Threat Intelligence.

Oliver was responsible for liaising with the client for business requirements and architectural direction and mentors a small team of junior developers.

Contribution: While the team are largely afforded the freedom to experiment and innovate, using scrum methods, Oliver provided the team with thought leadership and technical direction, during times of uncertainty, and also got involved with creating designs and proofs of concept for larger more complicated work scheduled for future sprints.

The Cyber Threat Intelligence capability was delivered to the client, who are successfully using the application and continuing its development.

Oliver also created a starter project for the team to develop their next product: a GDPR search application. This project was created with React and the Material UI framework, using a mobile first responsive web design, and Jest as the unit test framework. Dependencies were also configured for code styling, with StandardJS, and documentation with JSDoc.

Developer

Marwell Zoo | Jul 2019 - Sept 2019

Project name: IoT Zoo

Collaborating with Marwell Zoo and Infinitely Simple UK, on a project championed by IBM UK CTO Andy Stanford-Clark, Oliver used IoT and machine learning to reduce the cost of heating the zoo's animal houses.

By using some simple hardware, IBM Watson, Node-RED and Python, animals can be detected and heated only when they need it; currently reducing energy consumption by 10%, with scope for further reductions.

https://www.ibm.com/blogs/internet-of-things/iot-how-to-build-a-better-zoo-bed

Contribution: Oliver contributed to the Node-RED and Python development, as well as presenting the working solution at the IBM Festival of Innovation.

Developer

Public Sector | Apr 2017 - Oct 2019

A new capability to deliver agile capacity for public sector. This first of a kind software factory comprising several development teams based in IBM Hursley



to develop and maintain new applications, using scrum based agile methodology. The factory was launched in April 2017 with a small number of teams that during the mobilisation phase have had to set up their own development and test environments, producing guides for future teams to use. They have then gone onto build new, bespoke applications, using primarily open source software and Atlassian tool suite. Using a DevSecOps approach, applications will be built through continuous integration to build, test and deploy each application, with an aim to release into production on a frequent basis.

Contribution: Oliver worked in various scrum teams, developing web applications, conforming to public sector security and accessibility standards, scalable RESTful APIs, big data pipelines and robotic process automation.

Developer

Home Office | Feb 2017 - Mar 2017

Project name: NLEDP

Large scale programme to replace end-of-life systems, of national importance, with a modern, scalable solution.

Contribution: Oliver applied his existing knowledge to help shape the design of the core relational database, as well as learning to design and build enterprise grade real-time search engines.

In the absence of a DevOps team during project mobilisation, Oliver has also learned to automate deployment of applications in containers, through industry leading cluster management platforms while adhering to Government Digital Services standards.

Bench Focal Point

IBM Client Innovation Centre - UK | Feb 2017 - Feb 2017

Managing the process of assigning CIC CSPs to client projects.

Contribution: Oliver worked with management across the UK CICs to ensure any CSPs (on the bench or imminently rolling off projects) were proposed and accepted for relevant client projects. This included daily revision of open seats, proposing CSPs for project roles, managing interviews with account teams and ensuring CSPs had everything required to start their assignments successfully. During Oliver's time as BFP, the Hursley bench reduced by over 50%.

Developer

IBM Client Innovation Centre – UK | Nov 2016 - Feb 2017

Personal improvement and automation training coordination.

Contribution: Oliver spent his bench time familiarising himself with front-end development languages, including JavaScript and Angular, as well as coordinating Robotic Process Automation training, using the Blue Prism platform, for suitable candidates from across the UK CICs, with the goal of building a foundation skill pool, for anticipated billable work in the Intelligent Automation Practice.

Additional information

https://github.com/ojwm

